hey everyone welcome back to our Channel
I am back with another interesting topic
in the Tosca automation playlist
so now we are going to talk about how we
can create and manage branches in Tosca
workspaces
now if you are working in a multi-user
workspace and you are working in a big
team uh where you have got different
Tosca automation Specialists working on
the same project or different releases
of the same project or the application
itself right
you have to find a way of how you can
basically work separately on different
features or different releases right so
different people will be developing
different test cases for uh same
application or different application
but you need to find a way how you can
manage all these different work and then
merge everything into one place so that
that can be used in the coming up
release right or in the next automation
run when you want to run all the test
cases which have been developed recently
by all these different Oscar automation
specialists
to do this Tosca also provides you with
a feature where you can create different
branches and you can basically merge
these branches into the master branch
and then you can also delete these
branches right
so the concept which Tosca follows is
pretty much similar to the git workflow
which is displayed here you can see
there is a main branch right so the
slide blue color this is the main branch
and you can see there are different
versions of this main branch but
then there are development branches okay
so this purple color are all the
development branches and they could be
linked to a particular version okay now
each development branch is independent
of uh each other right so any developer
who is uh has created a branch from this
version 0.1 can work on its own features
and once it is completed uh it can merge
his changes to this version zero one
right and then start working on 0.2 so
this way it will be easier to manage uh
different features uh where different
developers are working and nobody will
be basically overwriting or overriding
changes of some other developer right
everybody will be working independently
but at a later point of time when all
the features are completed you can merge
everything into the master Branch or the
main branch okay so that's the concept
uh which is followed in the source code
repository like git or any other SCM
tool if you have worked upon and the Sim
concept applies for Tosca as well
so you can create different branches
from a master Branch okay so your
multi-user workspace uh will be your
master branch which you have created and
then as an admin you can create
different branches out of this master
Branch right and then uh from that uh
branches which has been created by the
Admin different Tosca users can work on
those branches they can create their own
repository or uh they can create their
own workspace out of that branch and
they can keep on working on that
repository which has got that Branch
okay and once they are finished then the
admin will come back and it will merge
that Branch to the master Branch
obviously there if there are any
conflicts uh it will be either merged or
removed right and this way you can
manage your Tosca workspace much better
if everybody starts working on the same
Master workspace then it will be very
hard to manage and also very hard to
maintain in the long run
okay so this way you can resolve
conflicts easily you can also work on
different uh test cases for different
applications without impacting the main
workspace okay
so uh this is uh the concept of creating
branches and managing branches but let's
have a look in Tosca in jail time how it
looks like how we can create branches
okay
now coming back to Tosca uh we can
launch our multi-user workspace from
where we can create different branches
so we can consider this as our Master
Branch this contains all our shared
libraries all our main test cases and
all our modules right requirements
everything and this is the main branch
right for our project now there are
different people in the team who want to
work on different test cases and they
want to work on different releases right
so what we'll do we will come to this
main branch we'll log in as an admin
and then we are going to create branches
for these different users who are going
to work on different releases or
different features some additional
features which we want to add to this
particular project right
so for this uh right click on the root
project and there you will find an
option called create Branch Okay click
on that it will ask you for a branch
name
so I will say multi and RC one right so
which is maybe a release candidate one
right so that's my first branch
and once you do this you will see that
it will give you a message that it was
created successfully
also in order to work with the new
Branch we need to save all changes to
our current workspace close the
workspace and then create a new
workspace with this new branch which is
called the multi-rc fund right so all
the steps are already mentioned here we
just need to follow all these three
steps okay
so what we are going to do uh we have to
check in all okay so although I have
already checked in everything and then
we have to close this project
our workspace
and now we need to open or create a new
workspace with our new Branch okay so
that's uh the previous workspace was
with the master Branch okay so you don't
need to make any changes into the master
branch and that's why we have created a
new branch and now with this new Branch
we should create a new workspace as well
okay
so for this
um again I am going to select sqlite
okay
and this time around you can see I can
use the use existing repository uh this
check mark is there
and I have already a repository you can
see this is my common repository for my
multi-buck multi-user workspace right
and then we have got another field here
called Branch right now by default it
will be Master but if you have created
more branches you will get it here so go
ahead and select this multi rc1 branch
and then we will create a new workspace
for this okay so we will call it rc1
okay
and then create this new workspace
so now this new workspace is being
created with a branch from the master
Branch right so this is like a branch
which where we can do our changes
without affecting the master Branch okay
and we have got a separate repository
for this Branch as well
okay so now um again we have to we can
use the same user if you have created
more users you can use that as well
okay and let's go to our project now
here is the project
now even though the workspace name is
same if you go on the top you will see
the Tosca Commander multi demo and the
path of this uh particular repository it
is
rc1.tws okay and the branch is multi rc1
even though the name is same it is not
the same workspace the branch is
different so whatever changes you make
here will not affect the master Branch
okay
so let's see now if I go ahead and
create another test case here so let's
check this out
and I am going to create a new test case
here okay going to name it TC3 now
so this is what I have changed here
let's go ahead check in all okay
now we have seen how we can create a
branch from the master Branch right now
once we have made changes we have
completed our all our changes in this
particular Branch we want to merge these
changes back into the master Branch
right so everything is tested everything
is working fine now let's go back and
merge these changes okay
so how you can do that checking your
changes and then close this particular
repository okay or workspace
and then let's go ahead and open our
multi-demo project okay
and we will enter the password Here
and here uh now
again you can check uh the workspace
name is same but you can see the path is
different and the branch is Master okay
so do take note of this although uh in
real world this will not happen like
this I mean currently I am the only user
here who is managing all these different
things but generally there will be an
admin who will be managing the master
Branch okay and then there will be
different uh testers who will be working
on their own branches so what they will
do uh once they have completed they will
notify the admin and the admin will log
into the master branch and then he will
merge all the branches which have been
completed okay so it won't be one single
user there will be different users but
for now uh I am doing all the works so
it may sound or it may seem a little bit
confusing okay
okay but here now we are in the master
Branch so when you right click on this
you will also see an option called merge
branch
and this is how you will merge different
branches back to the master Branch okay
now you can see by default it has
selected the multi-rc one because I
don't have any other branches but you
have got if you have got more branches
then you can select any of the branch to
get merged uh into the master Branch
okay it will give you a warning the
branch will permanently delete it when
you check in the up changed objects okay
so
now we will merge the changes here and
let's go here
and here you will see that we have got
now a third test case which is DC3 it
came from the different branch which I
had created rc1 right so I have added
the TC3 there and now you can see those
has been merged into the master branch
and we can see here it's been updated
okay
so this is how you can uh see that
without affecting our Master repository
right from a master workspace we are
making changes uh we are making changes
at a different level not at the Master
Level and this makes our maintenance
easier right also uh nothing can
basically enter into the master
repository without being properly tested
and executed okay so this will make sure
that your master is always working as
expected and no unnecessary changes are
being made into the master workspace
right so whatever changes people want to
work on they will work on the branches
but uh nothing should come into the
master Branch without being tested
properly and without being executed okay
so now the last step which is remaining
in this particular workflow is to delete
a particular Branch okay
so you can delete branches like this you
right click on the project and then
click on delete Branch now it is saying
no branches available to delete and that
is because
uh when we merge the ma Branch to the
master Branch uh that particular Branch
was already deleted okay but if you have
more branches you can just right click
and go to delete Branch okay
so these are the three functionality
which is available create Branch merge
branch and delete branch and using these
three functionalities uh you can work on
a branching workflow which is very
similar to any uh source code management
repository like git or GitHub or there
are many source code repositories if you
have previously worked on you will
understand how it works and the same
concept can be applied into the Tosca
workspaces to make it more maintainable
more sustainable and to make it uh
error free going forward right so that
we have a clean master branch and then
we'll we can provide different branch
feature branches to all the different
developers or testers who are working on
different Oscar projects or features
that's all for this particular video if
you have any questions then please leave
it in the comments
if you like this video then please
subscribe to our Channel
thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next video